Edith Jacobson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edith Jacobson Papers 1922-1977
MSS59360
Jacobson, Edith
2,800 items
14 containers plus 1 oversize
5.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst. Correspondence, writings, artwork, and other papers chiefly relating to Jacobson's psychiatric practice, psychoanalysis, the study and treatment of depression, and object relations theory.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Jacobson, Edith.
Subjects
Depression, Mental.; Imprisonment--Psychological aspects.; Object relations (Psychoanalysis); Political refugees--Germany.; Political refugees--United States.; Psychiatry--Practice--Germany--Berlin.; Psychiatry--Practice--New York (State)--New York.; Psychoanalysis.; Women political prisoners--Germany.
Places
Germany--History--1933-1945.
Occupations
Psychiatrists.; Psychoanalysts.
Provenance
The papers of Edith Jacobson, psychoanalyst, were donated to the Library of Congress by the Sigmund Freud Archives in 1980.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Edith Jacobson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1897, Sept. 10 Born, Haynau, Germany
1922 Received medical degree, University of Munich, Munich, Germany
1922 1925 Pediatric internship, University Hospital, Heidelberg, Germany Internship and residency in internal medicine, Munich University Hospital, Munich, Germany
1925 1928 Residencies, Oppenheim Neurological Clinic and Department of Psychiatry, Charité Hospital, Berlin, Germany
1925 1929 Psychoanalytical training, Berlin Psychoanalytic Institute, Berlin, Germany
1929 Began practice of psychiatry and psychoanalysis, Berlin, Germany
1934 Appointed training analyst, Berlin Psychoanalytic Institute, Berlin, Germany
1935 1938 Imprisoned by Nazis for refusal to give information on patients to the Gestapo
1938 Escaped from Germany and emigrated to the United States
1940 1977 Private psychoanalytic practice, New York, N.Y.
1942 Appointed training analyst, New York Psychoanalytic Institute, New York, N.Y.; served as member of faculty and on educational committee
1964 Published The Self and the Object World. New York: International University Press
1971 Published Depression: Comparative Studies of Normal, Neurotic, and Psychotic Conditions. New York: International University Press
1978, Dec. 8 Died, Rochester, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edith Jacobson (1897-1978) span the years 1922 to 1977 and relate primarily to her career as a psychoanalyst. They include correspondence, writings, artwork, and a small amount of other professional and personal items. Much of the professional writing is in English, but most of the correspondence and poetry is in German.
Writings by Edith Jacobson and her colleagues in the field of psychoanalysis comprise the major portion of the collection. Topics include the study and treatment of depression and depressive conditions and object relations theory. One of Jacobson's early papers examines the psychological effects of imprisonment on female political prisoners and is based on her observations while being held as a prisoner by the Nazis before World War II. A brief description of her own experience as a prisoner can be found in a compilation of unpublished short stories and essays entitled "The American Oak Tree."
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1936-1977
Writings, 1935-1977
Miscellany, 1922-circa 1970
Oversize, undated
Container List
- Correspondence, 1936-1977 (Box 1-2)
  Letters received and a few copies of letters sent, primarily of a personal nature. Most in German.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically therein.
  - Faerber, Helene, 1937-1940, undated (Box 1)
  - Jacobson, Pelagia, 1939-1943 (Box 1)
  - Jossmann, Paul B. (Box 1)
    - 1939-1941, undated, (8 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1942-1949, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1950, 1957, 1972-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Writings, 1935-1977 (Box 3-14)
  Drafts and typescripts of books, papers, reviews, critiques, and poetry by Jacobson and papers and poetry written by others.
  Arranged by type of material, then alphabetically by name of author and chronologically therein.
  - By Jacobson (Box 3)
    - Books (Box 3)
      - "The American Oak Tree," undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Depression: Comparative Studies of Normal, Neurotic, and Psychotic Conditions, 1953-1957, 1966, undated, (9 folders); (5 folders) (Box 3, Box 4)
      - The Self and the Object World, undated, (6 folders); (4 folders) (Box 4, Box 5)
    - Notebook, 1935-1938, undated (Box 5)
    - Papers and presentations (Box 5)
      - 1949-1953, (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1954-1966, (9 folders) (Box 6)
      - 1967-1975, undated, (7 folders0 (Box 7)
    - Poetry 1940-1952, undated (Box 7)
    - Reviews and critiques, 1951-1963, 1971-1973, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - Unidentified drafts and fragments, undated, (4 folders); (2 folders) (Box 8, Box 9)
  - By others (Box 9)
    - Papers and presentations (Box 9)
      - Altschul, Sol, 1965 (Box 9)
      - Axelrod, Sidney, undated (Box 9)
      - Bach, Sheldon See Container 13, Schwartz, Lester, and Sheldon Bach (Box 9)
      - Badal, Daniel W., undated (Box 9)
      - Bak, Robert C., undated (Box 9)
      - Beres, David, 1957, 1965, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Bergmann, Martin S., circa 1977 (Box 9)
      - Blos, Peter, 1962-1967 (Box 9)
      - Brenner, Charles, 1957, undated (Box 9)
      - Brodey, Warren M., undated (Box 9)
      - Calder, Kenneth, undated (Box 10)
      - Cook, John A., 1962 (Box 10)
      - Deutsch, Helene, undated (Box 10)
      - Engel, Eva H., 1947 (Box 10)
      - Fisher, Charles, undated (Box 10)
      - Freud, Anna, 1952 (Box 10)
      - Frosch, John, undated (Box 10)
      - Gaddini, Eugenio, undated (Box 10)
      - Gill, Merton M. See Container 11, Klein, George S., and Merton M. Gill (Box 10)
      - Greenacre, Phyllis, 1952, undated (Box 10)
      - Greenson, Ralph R., 1951-1952, undated (Box 10)
      - Gross, Alfred, 1954-1956, undated (Box 10)
      - Grossman, William I., circa 1961, undated (Box 10)
      - Guttman, Samuel A., 1965 (Box 10)
      - Harrison, Irving, 1964 (Box 10)
      - Harvard Symposium on Object Loss, undated (Box 10)
      - Heiman, Marcel, undated (Box 10)
      - Joffe, W. G., and Joseph Sandler, undated See also Container 13, Sandler, Joseph, and W. G. Joffe (Box 10)
      - Joseph, Edward D., circa 1962 (Box 10)
      - Katan, M., undated (Box 11)
      - Kernberg, Otto F., 1977 (Box 11)
      - Kestenberg, Judith S., 1965, undated (Box 11)
      - Klein, George S., 1965-1966 (Box 11)
      - Klein, George S., and Merton M. Gill, 1961, undated (Box 11)
      - Kramer, Edith, undated (Box 11)
      - Kris, Ernst, 1955 (Box 11)
      - Kronfeld, M. [?], undated (Box 11)
      - Krupp, George R., undated (Box 11)
      - Lewis, Helen B. See Container 13, Witkin, Herman A., and Helen B. Lewis (Box 11)
      - Lichtenstein, H., undated (Box 11)
      - Lipin, Theodore, 1963 (Box 11)
      - Loewenstein, Rudolph M., circa 1962 (Box 11)
      - Mahler, Margaret S., 1957 For additional information See Container 10, Harvard Symposium on Object Loss (Box 11)
      - Meng, Heinrich, 1954 (Box 11)
      - Milrod, David, undated (Box 11)
      - Nagera, Humberto, 1964 (Box 11)
      - Natterson, Joseph M., 1965 (Box 12)
      - Pao, Ping-Nie, undated (Box 12)
      - Peterfreund, Emanuel, 1964, undated, (2 folders) (Box 12)
      - Post, Seymour C., 1966 (Box 12)
      - Provence, Sally See Container 10, Harvard Symposium on Object Loss (Box 12)
      - Rapaport, David, 1950-1951, undated, (5 folders) (Box 12)
      - Reich, Annie, undated (Box 12)
      - Reider, Arthur E., 1967 (Box 12)
      - Ritvo, Samuel See Container 10, Harvard Symposium on Object Loss (Box 13)
      - Ritvo, Samuel, and Albert J. Solnit, undated (Box 13)
      - Rochlin, Gregory See Container 10, Harvard Symposium on Object Loss (Box 13)
      - Rubinfine, David L., 1961 (Box 13)
      - Sandler, Joseph, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Sandler, Joseph, and W. G. Joffe, 1965 See also Container 10, Joffe, W. G., and Joseph Sandler (Box 13)
      - Scharl, Adele E., undated (Box 13)
      - Schecter, David E., 1965 (Box 13)
      - Schur, Max, undated (Box 13)
      - Schwartz, Lester, and Sheldon Bach, undated (Box 13)
      - Shambaugh, Benjamin See Container 10, Harvard Symposium on Object (Box 13)
      - Loss Silving, Helen, 1965 (Box 13)
      - Solnit, Albert J. See Container 13, Ritvo, Samuel, and Albert J. Solnit (Box 13)
      - Sirota, Milton See Container 13, Weisfogel, Jerry, and Milton Sirota (Box 13)
      - Spitz, René A., 1950 (Box 13)
      - Wallach, H. D. See Container 10, Harvard Symposium on Object Loss (Box 13)
      - Weisfogel, Jerry, and Milton Sirota, undated (Box 13)
      - Witkin, Herman A., and Helen B. Lewis, 1964 (Box 13)
      - Woodbury, Michael A., 1965 (Box 13)
    - Poetry, 1939-1948, undated, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Unidentified, 1954, 1964, undated, (6 folders) (Box 14)
- Miscellany, 1922-circa 1970 (Box 14)
  Pencil sketches, charcoal drawings, watercolors, reports of professional meetings, and a few personal items.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Artwork, undated See also Oversize, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Personal items, 1939, 1945, undated (Box 14)
  - Study group meeting minutes and other professional material, 1922, 1939, 1959-1964, circa 1970, undated (Box 14)
- Oversize, undated (Box OV 1)
  Drawings.
  Described according to the series, folder, and container from which the items were removed.
  - Artwork, undated (Container 14) (Box OV 1)